<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<qXML>
<!--frame>
<question>
    <clinical>
        </clinical>
           
    <qImage></qImage>
    <mainQ>
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a></a>
        <b></b>
        <c></c>
        <d></d>
        <e></e>
        </choices>
    <answer></answer>
    <exp>
        </exp>
    <aImage>
        </aImage>
    <ref></ref>
</question-->

<!--chb ppm mode-->
<question>
    <clinical>For the following patient undergoing pacemaker implantation,
        </clinical>
           
    <qImage>media/CHB.png</qImage>
    <mainQ>What would be the least appropriate mode?
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>AAI</a>
        <b>DDI</b>
        <c>DDD</c>
        <d>VDD</d>
        <e>VVI</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>A</answer>
    <exp>Tracing = high grade AV block. Ventricular pacing is required. AAI is contraindicated.
        </exp>
    <aImage>media/ppmCode.jpg
        </aImage>
    <ref>NA</ref>
</question>

<!--ppm syndrome-->
<question>
    <clinical>NA</clinical>
           
    <qImage>NA</qImage>
    <mainQ>Which of the following pacing modes does not cause pacemaker syndrome?
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>VVI</a>
        <b>VDD</b>
        <c>DDD</c>
        <d>AAI</d>
        <e>None of the above</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>E</answer>
    <exp>Pacemaker syndrome can occur in any type of pacemaker, but most commonly with VVI, and VVIR.
    Symptoms relate to Atrioventricular dyssynchrony including shortness of breath, dizziness, fatigue, pulsations in the neck or abdomen, cough.
    In DDD, abnormal sensing in atrial channel can cause pacemaker syndrome.
    In AAI, marked AV prolongation may cause pacemaker syndrome.
    In VDD, a prolong episode of sinus arrest may trigger pacemaker syndrome.
        </exp>
    <aImage>NA</aImage>
    <ref>NA</ref>
</question>

<!--optimal mode-->
<question>
    <clinical>A 75-year-old woman presents to her cardiologist’s office with the complaint of dizziness. Her ECG revealed complete AV block. During exercise, her sinus rate only goes to 90 bpm.
    </clinical>
           
    <qImage>NA</qImage>
    <mainQ>Which of the following would be the optimal pacing mode for this patient?
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>AAI</a>
        <b>VDD</b>
        <c>VVI</c>
        <d>DDD</d>
        <e>DDDR</e>
    </choices>
    <answer>E</answer>
    <exp>The presence of AV block indicates the need for ventricular pacing, and thus, excludes AAI pacing. The inability of the sinus rates to go above 70 bpm indicates the need for rate-adaptive atrial pacing. 
    DDDR combines atrial pacing that can meet metabolic demands of exertion. 
        </exp>
    <aImage>media/optMode.png
        </aImage>
    <ref>https://www.escardio.org/Guidelines/Clinical-Practice-Guidelines/Cardiac-Pacing-and-Cardiac-Resynchronization-Therapy</ref>
</question>

<!--dual over single-->
<question>
    <clinical>NA</clinical>
           
    <qImage>NA</qImage>
    <mainQ>Which of the following is not the advantage of dual chamber over single chamber pacemaker?
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>Reduce incidence of pacemaker syndrome.</a>
        <b>Reduce incidence of AF.</b>
        <c>Reduce incidence of stroke.</c>
        <d>Improve exercise capacity.</d>
        <e>Lower rate of lead dislodgement.</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>E</answer>
    <exp>In patients with SSS, 
    dual chamber was associated with lower rate of AF and stroke; but not HF or death. 
    Symptoms and exercise capacity are improved more dual chamber than single chamber in both SSS and AV block.
    Dual chamber devices, however, are more expensive owing to the additional lead, longer implantation times and
    higher risk of complications.
        </exp>
    <aImage>media/dualVsSingle.png</aImage>
    <ref>https://www.escardio.org/Guidelines/Clinical-Practice-Guidelines/Cardiac-Pacing-and-Cardiac-Resynchronization-Therapy</ref>
</question>

<!--bipolar lead-->
<question>
    <clinical>NA</clinical>
    <qImage>NA</qImage>
    <mainQ>An advanctage of bipolar over unipolar leads is:
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>Less susceptible to electromechanical interference.</a>
        <b>Smaller lead.</b>
        <c>Smaller generator.</c>
        <d>Less susceptible to lead fracture.</d>
        <e>They can cause muscle stimulation.</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>A</answer>
    <exp>The modern pacemaker leads are bipolar leads. They consists of two electrical channels encased in an insulating material. One channel conducts the electrical impulse towards the lead tip and the other channel completes the circuit back to the pacemaker.
    In unipolar systems, the anode was the pacemaker canister (can) and it is in contact with the pectoralis major muscle at the pacemaker pocket floor.
    Bipolar system is more preferred due to less myopotential sensing and stimulation.
        </exp>
    <aImage>media/uniBipolar.jpg
        </aImage>
    <ref>https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1111/j.1540-8159.1991.tb02887.x</ref>
</question>

<!--noncapture-->
<question>
    <clinical>A 65-year-old man presents to the emergency department after a syncopal event. He was eating dinner and was witnessed to abruptly fall back in his chair for several seconds before regaining consciousness. His past history includes atrial fibrillation and hypertension. He tells you that 15 years ago, he received a pacemaker because “his heart stopped.” A generator change was performed 5 years ago. He has regular pacemaker checks; the last one was 3 months ago, and he was told everything was fine. His medications include warfarin, metoprolol, and lisinopril.
        
        On examination, his blood pressure is 140/80 mm Hg with a heart rate of 75 bpm. The physical examination is unremarkable. A pacemaker programmer is available to you if needed. As you speak to him, his eyes roll back and a telemetry strip is recorded (as shown).
    </clinical>
           
    <qImage>media/noncapture.png</qImage>
    <mainQ>
        Which of the following should be your next step in management of this patient?
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>Increase the ventricular sensitivity of the pacemaker.</a>
        <b>Place a magnet over the device.</b>
        <c>Initiate external pacing with cutaneous patches.</c>
        <d>Place a temporary pacemaker.</d>
        <e>Increase the ventricular output of the pacemaker.</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>E
        </answer>
    <exp>Tracing = loss of ventricular capture in an underlying rhythm of complete heart block. 
        Pacing lead is 15 years old so lead problem is highly possible. 
        Interrogation will reveal and temporary fix the cause if it is readily available as in this case. 
        There is no issue of inappropriate sensing so magnet or adjusting sensitivity would not help.
        </exp>
    <aImage>NA</aImage>
    <ref>NA</ref>
</question>

<!--ppm syndrome ecg-->
<question>
    <clinical>DDD 70/110, AV delay 175, PVARP 275.
    Patient complaint of fatigue and shortness of breath.
        </clinical>
           
    <qImage>media/ppmSyndrome.png</qImage>
    <mainQ>Which of the following pacemaker parameters should be adjusted to improve the symptoms?</mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>Atrial pacing stimulation output</a>
        <b>Atrial sensitivity</b>
        <c>Ventricular pacing stimulation output</c>
        <d>Ventricular sensitivity</d>
        <e>AV delay</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>A</answer>
    <exp>The atrial pacing is not captured. The retrograde VA conduction is then able to capture the atrium 
    causing the pacemaker syndrome. The first step is to increase the atrial output.
        </exp>
    <aImage>NA</aImage>
    <ref>NA</ref>
</question>

<!--PMT-->
<question>
    <clinical>DDD 60/110, AV delay 175, PVARP 360. 
    The top strip was taken when the patient had palpitation. The bottom strip was taken while the magnet was applied.
    </clinical>
           
    <qImage>media/PMT.jpg</qImage>
    <mainQ>What is the most likely cause of the rapid tracking observed in the top ECG strip? 
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>Loss of atrial capture.</a>
        <b>Loss of ventricular capture.</b>
        <c>Loss of atrial sensing.</c>
        <d>Loss of ventricular sensing.</d>
        <e>Rapid atrial rate.</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>A</answer>
    <exp>Top tracing: PMT. Bottom tracing: Loss of atrial capture. 
        </exp>
    <aImage>media/pmtAlgo.png
        </aImage>
    <ref>NA</ref>
</question>

<!--PVARP-->
<question>
    <clinical>NA</clinical>
           
    <qImage>NA</qImage>
    <mainQ>What is the principal purpose of post-ventricular atrial refractory perior (PVARP) in dual-chamber pacemaker timing cycle?
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>To prevent the ventricular sensing amplifier from sensing the far-field P wave.</a>
        <b>To limit the maximal atrial rate which ventricular pacing can track.</b>
        <c>To prevent ventricular oversensing of T wave.</c>
        <d>To prevent atrial oversensing of a retrograde atrial impulse.</d>
        <e>To prevent inhibition of ventricular pacing by electromechanical interference.</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>D</answer>
    <exp>The purpose of any refractory periods is to prevent the pacemaker for responding to inappropriate signals.
     PVARP is an atrial refractory period that occurs after a paced or sensed ventricular event.
    PVARP prevents the atrial channel from sensing the ventricular pacing pulse, the far-field QRS and
    retrograde P-waves.
        </exp>
    <aImage>media/dddTiming.jpg
        </aImage>
    <ref>NA</ref>
</question>

<!--wkb-->
<question>
    <clinical>A DDD pacemaker is programmed to a lower rate limit of 50 bpm, an upper rate limit of  125 bpm, and an AV delay of 175 ms that is reduced by 25 ms at an atrial rate of 100 bpm and a post ventricular-atrial refractory period of 300 ms.
        </clinical>
           
    <qImage>NA</qImage>
    <mainQ>During a stress test when the atrial rate is 128 bpm, the ventricular response is most likely to be which of the following?
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>1:1 conduction</a>
        <b>2:1 AV block</b>
        <c>3:1 SA block</c>
        <d>Pseudo Mobitz II AV block</d>
        <e>Pseudo Wenckebach AV block</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>E</answer>
    <exp>URL = 125/min = 480 msec. Wenkebach 450-480 msec = 125-133/min.
        </exp>
    <aImage>media/upperRate.jpg
        </aImage>
    <ref>NA</ref>
</question>

<!--undersensing-->
<question>
    <clinical>Temporary venous pacemaker. Setting: VVI 75bpm, output 5mA, sensitivity 5 mV. 
        </clinical>
           
    <qImage>media/vvi undersense.jpg</qImage>
    <mainQ>What is the next appropriate management?</mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>Adjust sensitivity to 7mV.</a>
        <b>Adjust sensitivity to 2.5mV.</b>
        <c>Adjust output to 10mA.</c>
        <d>Reposition the lead.</d>
        <e>Continue to follow up clinically.</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>B</answer>
    <exp>Tracing: V undersensing. Making it more sensitive or lowering the sensitivity number 
    should be the first thing to do, rather than repositioning the lead.
        </exp>
    <aImage>NA</aImage>
    <ref>NA</ref>
</question>

<!--cautery-->
<question>
    <clinical>A 50 year-old lady with history of complete heart block s/p PPM is undergoing an abdominal surgery.
    During the surgery, the below tracing is observed while the cautery is being applied.
        </clinical>
           
    <qImage>media/Voversensing.JPG</qImage>
    <mainQ>What would be the most appropriate management?</mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>Increase ventricular output.</a>
        <b>Reduce ventricular sensitivity.</b>
        <c>Apply magnet over the pacemaker.</c>
        <d>Dopamine drip.</d>
        <e>Terminate the procedure immediately.</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>C</answer>
    <exp>Failure to pace is noted, likely due to oversensing from EMI from cautery. 
    Adjusting the ventricular sensitivity alone is not enough due to the high frequency nature of the cautery.
    Since the patient is pacemaker dependent (she is being V-paced in every beat in the tracing),
    switching to asynchronous mode either by programming or magnet application is recommended.
    </exp>
    <aImage>media/cautery.png</aImage>
    <ref>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S073510971637067X</ref>
</question>

<!--track AF-->
<question>
    <clinical>64F s/p DDD pacemaker is in the ICU after a colectomy.
        </clinical>
           
    <qImage>media/trackAf.png</qImage>
    <mainQ>What would be the most likely reason for the frequent rapid ventricular pacing in this patient?
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>Atrial oversensing.</a>
        <b>Inappropriate programming.</b>
        <c>Normal functioning.</c>
        <d>Ventricular undersensing.</d>
        <e>Runaway pacemaker.</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>C</answer>
    <exp>Tracing = AF with intermittent V pacing. The pacing rate was irregular. The P wave was not seen.
    This is likely atrial fibrillation with V tracking the atrial signal. Some atrial signals likely 
    fell into the refractory period. With the irregularity nature of AF, the V pacing is irregular as well. 
    The V rate, even if it was fast, it was not faster than 100 bpm, which likely to be the upper rate limit.
    There were a few native QRS beats which were appropriately sensed. The device will, at a later time, go into
    a mode switching to DDI. 
        </exp>
    <aImage>media/dddTiming.jpg</aImage>
    <ref>NA</ref>
</question>

<!--drug and stim threshold-->
<question>
    <clinical>NA</clinical>
           
    <qImage>NA</qImage>
    <mainQ>Which of the following drugs is most likely to elevate myocardial stimulation threshold 
    after implantation of a dual-chamber pacemaker?
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>Digoxin</a>
        <b>Diltiazem</b>
        <c>Flecainide</c>
        <d>Mexiletine</d>
        <e>Sotalol</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>C</answer>
    <exp>Class IC antiarrhythmic agents are notoriously known to increase pacing threshold. 
    Digoxin, exercise, epinephrine are known to reduce pacing threshold.  
        </exp>
    <aImage>media/aadThreshold.png
        </aImage>
    <ref>https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1880427611800529</ref>
</question>

<!--infection-->
<question>
    <clinical>
    A 66-year-old woman with hypertension underwent dual-chamber pacemaker implantation 7 years ago due to symptomatic sinus node dysfunction. She has no other prior medical history. Six weeks ago, she was treated for a mild lower-extremity cellulitis. 
    She comes into your office today complaining of 4 days of soreness in the pacemaker pocket. Physical examination reveals erythema, swelling, and tenderness at the pacemaker pocket, without drainage. She is afebrile and the white blood cell count is normal. A transthoracic echocardiogram is normal.
        </clinical>
           
    <qImage>NA</qImage>
    <mainQ>Which of the following would be most appropriate at this time?</mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>Begin intravenous (IV) antibiotics, debride the pacemaker pocket, and replace the pacemaker pulse generator.</a>
        <b>Begin IV antibiotics, debride the pacemaker pocket, remove the pulse generator, and extract all the pacemaker leads.</b>
        <c>Begin IV antibiotics, then remove the pacemaker pulse generator if no improvement in 2 weeks.</c>
        <d>Begin oral antibiotics, then remove the pacemaker pulse generator and all pacemaker leads if no improvement in 2 weeks.</d>
        <e>Observe without further therapy at this time.</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>B</answer>
    <exp>Pocket infection. Be aggressive!</exp>
    <aImage>media/infection.png</aImage>
    <ref>https://www.heartrhythmjournal.com/article/S1547-5271(17)31080-9/fulltext</ref>
</question>

<!--fusion-->
<question>
    <clinical>DDD</clinical>
           
    <qImage>media/fusionQ.png</qImage>
    <mainQ>How is the pacemaker function?
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>Normal function</a>
        <b>A undersensing</b>
        <c>V undersensing</c>
        <d>A non-capture</d>
        <e>V non-capture</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>A</answer>
    <exp>At the 2nd and 5th beats, V pacing comes right at the time of the native beats; small degree
    of fusions noted.
        </exp>
    <aImage>media/fusionA.jpg</aImage>
    <ref>NA</ref>
</question>

<!--post CV-->
<question>
    <clinical>
    A patient undergoes a cardioversion six months after undergoing implantation of a dual chamber pacemaker (DDD 60/140). After the cardioversion, the ECG monitor shows ventricular pacing at 65 bpm with no evidence of either atrial pacing or tracking.
    Pacemaker interrogation reveals normal pacing parameters.
        </clinical>
           
    <qImage>NA</qImage>
    <mainQ>Which one of the following is the most appropriate course of action?
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>Obtain a chest X-ray.</a>
        <b>Replace the generator.</b>
        <c>Reprogram the pacemaker.</c>
        <d>Place a temporary pacemaker.</d>
        <e>Place a magnet over the pacemaker</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>C</answer>
    <exp>Cardioversion causes power-on-reset resulting in the pacemaker to revert the pacing mode to VVI.
    The threshold and impedance are generally not affected.
    Reprogramming the device is the most appropriate thing to do.
        </exp>
    <aImage>media/emiPOR.png</aImage>
    <ref>http://www.onlinejacc.org/content/69/2/189</ref>
</question>

<!--CRT non pacing during Sinus Tachy-->
<question>
    <clinical>
        A 66 year old woman with a nonischemic cardiomyopathy, LBBB received a CRT-D device 2 months ago. 
        The device is programmed DDDR, 60-125 bpm. She is now hospitalized with pneumonia. 
    </clinical>
    <qImage>media/crtInST.png</qImage>
    <mainQ>
        The most likely explanation for the above tracing is:
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>Loss of RV capture.</a>
        <b>Sinus rate above upper limit.</b>
        <c>Loss of LV capture.</c>
        <d>Loss of both RV and LV capture.</d>
        <e>Pacemaker mediated tachycardia.</e>
    </choices>
    <answer>B</answer>
    <exp>
    The initial part of the ECG shows sinus tachycardia with BiV pacing. 
    When the sinus rate is above 125bpm (=upper rate limit), the device fails to track. 
    The rhythm then is sinus tachycardia with LBBB. 
        </exp>
    <aImage>media/bivVector.png
        </aImage>
    <ref>https://academic.oup.com/europace/article/15/3/376/432909</ref>
</question>

</qXML>