<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<qXML>


<!--noncapture-->
<question>
    <clinical>
        A 65-year-old man presents to the emergency department after a syncopal event. 
        He was eating dinner and was witnessed to abruptly fall back in his chair for 
        several seconds before regaining consciousness. His past history includes atrial 
        fibrillation and hypertension. He tells you that 15 years ago, he received a pacemaker 
        because “his heart stopped.” A generator change was performed 5 years ago. 
        He has regular pacemaker checks; the last one was 3 months ago, and he was told 
        everything was fine. His medications include warfarin, metoprolol, and lisinopril.
        <part2>
        On examination, his blood pressure is 140/80 mm Hg with a heart rate of 75 bpm. 
        The physical examination is unremarkable. A pacemaker programmer is available to 
        you if needed. As you speak to him, his eyes roll back and a telemetry strip is recorded (as shown).
        </part2>
        </clinical>
    <qImage>media/noncapture.png</qImage>
    <mainQ>
        Which of the following should be your next step in management of this patient?
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>Increase the ventricular sensitivity of the pacemaker.</a>
        <b>Place a magnet over the device.</b>
        <c>Initiate external pacing with cutaneous patches.</c>
        <d>Place a temporary pacemaker.</d>
        <e>Increase the ventricular output of the pacemaker.</e>
        </choices>
    <answer>E
        </answer>
    <exp>Tracing = loss of ventricular capture in an underlying rhythm of complete heart block. 
        Pacing lead is 15 years old so lead problem is highly possible. 
        Interrogation will reveal and temporary fix the cause if it is readily available as in this case. 
        There is no issue of inappropriate sensing so magnet or adjusting sensitivity would not help.
        </exp>
    <aImage>
        </aImage>
</question>

<!--CRT non pacing during Sinus Tachy-->
<question>
    <clinical>
        A 66 year old woman with a nonischemic cardiomyopathy, LBBB received a CRT-D device 2 months ago. 
        The device is programmed DDDR, 60-125 bpm. She is now hospitalized with pneumonia. 
        <part2></part2>
    </clinical>
    <qImage>media/crtInST.png</qImage>
    <mainQ>
        The most likely explanation for the above tracing is:
        </mainQ>
    <choices>
        <a>Loss of RV capture.</a>
        <b>Sinus rate above upper limit.</b>
        <c>Loss of LV capture.</c>
        <d>Loss of both RV and LV capture.</d>
        <e>Pacemaker mediated tachycardia.</e>
    </choices>
    <answer>B</answer>
    <exp>
    The initial part of the ECG shows sinus tachycardia with BiV pacing. 
    When the sinus rate is above 125bpm (=upper rate limit), the device fails to track. 
    The rhythm then is sinus tachycardia with LBBB. 
        </exp>
    <aImage>media/bivVector.png
        </aImage>
</question>

</qXML>